it is 1:00.
And thank you all for joining us
in our next keynote session.
We are excited to have the curatorial team
for the Electronic Literature
Collection, volume five,
here to share with us their process
and some of the kind of challenges
and exciting things
they found on this journey.
The collection is always a monumental
undertaking, and perhaps even more
so now with AI generated works
and all of the questions they raise
as part of the landscape.
So, without further ado,
I turn it over to our
five team.
All right.
Thanks, Anastasia and hello everyone.
My name is Zach Whalen
and I'm happy on behalf of the ELC
five editorial Collective to
to get things started here today,
we're going to be talking about ELC five,
where we are so far and some observations
that we've been making as we go.
So whoops,
there we go.
So the rest of the team is Dan
Cox Ortega and Danny Espinosa.
And they are here and and waving.
So awesome.
All right.
So I want to start off just by providing
a bit of a very brief backstory
or history of the electronic literature
electronic literature collection.
I imagine many of you
in this audience are familiar with it.
But just in case not, this is a collection
that's published about every five years,
starting in 2006 with volume one,
and it's a work
of the electronic literature organization
that I think
does an important job with respect
to this field of electronic literature.
And to me, it's
a way of thinking about this question
what is electronic literature?
And over time, this question
and its answers have changed.
Different forms have predominated.
There are different audiences
for electronic literature,
and we find ourselves
facing different stakes
when we consider this question.
So as we think about each of these
collections,
prior volumes answering this question,
what is electronic literature?
It helps us think about
what does it mean for a particular work
to be collected in this collection
as an answer to that question
about what is electronic literature?
I'm not going to go into details
about that.
I mean,
I think there's there's a lot of rich
material to go into a deep dive about.
But one way I've been looking at
it is trying to understand each collection
in terms of its chronological scope,
looking at the works in it and seeing
which are
what is collected
and how they're distributed across time.
And it kind of gives a quick thumbnail
of that sense
of what is electronic literature
as you move through time.
So in 2006,
the works 60 works were collected,
spanned about 12 years,
focused on the recent history,
the immediately prior 12 years,
the median age three and a half years.
So many then contemporary works,
but spreading out a little bit.
The next collection spread out
quite a bit more and tried to,
I think, bring in more historical work
and spread that out
to a more diverse group of authors.
And AC three continue that
by quite a lot, by expanding that
by quite a lot, to include historically
significant works that were establishing
norms and and tropes that were continuing
to be influential throughout time.
So it has the widest spread, by far
the most distributed
chronological spread by far.
As we look at that,
LC four has a curve more similar
to ELC two, focusing on what was then
contemporary things going on.
Electronic literature in the year
2021, 2022 really answering that question.
And as we look at the works submitted.
So now this is a different in
but these are the work submitted for LC
five that we are considering.
There's a similar curve of things, many,
many things.
2025 is the largest column here.
And this is the year, the date
provided by people who shared their work.
And there were different interpretations
of how to use that date.
And this is a little bit
as you were were not provided.
So this is a little bit
vague, but that just gives you
a general sense of what we are
considering
as we tackle this big project of VLC five.
So for the rest of the talk,
we are going to be talking a bit
about the vision,
our call for submissions that we put out,
the review process that we've been working
through, our general timeline
and some general trends, themes and tropes
that we've started to notice
as we look through the material.
So with that, I will be
turning it over to whoever's
whoever goes next.
Is that is are you at next or.
Danny, I think it's me.
Great.
Okay, so
what I what what we want to talk about
here is kind of like
how it started, what we thought
we were going to get, what we asked for.
And that'll bring us to what we did get
and kind of what we're finding
as we're going through the review process.
So we did start the process
with a vision statement and
that we wanted to use to kind of ground
how we were approaching our
our role as editors.
And we had
we wanted to use the vision statement
and our kind of transparency
around the vision statement
as a way of foregrounding
what was really important to all of us,
which was being clear about our role
as editors and what kind of interests,
biases and priorities
we were bringing to the process.
Because that kind of transparency
is, like so easy to share now.
And I think it's so important
to foreground, not to pretend
that these are kind of easy
or obvious decisions,
like all of the decisions
and what we're asking for and,
and how we're deciding
what to include are informed by
and mostly these five primary priorities.
So the first one
is EDI or a general diversity
of particularly
authorship and communities
from which these works are emerging.
And so this has always been in some form
and interest in previous elves.
And we were especially inspired by the Elk
Forest explicit statements on
and work in prioritizing
equity, diversity and inclusion
in the kinds of works
and the kinds of communities
that they're reaching out to to include.
It's so easy to keep this
the these kind of anthologies
relatively closed and this kind of
community relatively close.
But it's also so,
so much more easy these days
to be able to reach out and contact new
connections, new linkages.
So that's been a priority.
And it's been
I'll speak for myself here, but
I think it's been really fruitful so far.
And we'll see some
of that emerging later on.
The second
priority that we were thinking about
is this idea of expansion
kind of connected to that, expanding
definitions
of what we mean by electronic literature,
what counts
as expanding the kinds of platforms
that are being used,
the kind of technology that's being used
in the kind of work that is resulting,
that really kind of seeing
where we had all put our lines around
what we thought
the electronic literature might mean,
and then kind of blasting those open.
And it's been, again,
really just like such an effective
and enlightening process
to see some submissions
that did still challenge us, challenge
the assumptions that we were making.
It's been a delay.
And number three is
AI with a big old question mark.
And it would be.
Irresponsible,
probably, or at least kind of
to have some limitations on to think about
doing an anthology like this right now
without considering AI.
We are absolutely interested in
and have been reading many submissions
that are directly responding
to the challenges and opportunities.
Cannot divorce one from the other
around the use of generative AI.
We have,
as you might imagine, received pushback
from all sides on this.
And we might talk about
some of that pushback more later.
But the one thing
we were really interested in
is one, transparency in the use of AI.
And to some kind of platform criticality.
We want you to be critical
of all platforms, not the least of which
is use of llms.
And we're interested also in community,
the number four
on these editorial priorities, communities
of practice, geographical communities, but
also especially nonacademic communities
and really trying reaching out.
You know, as I speak, as a half half
semi academic,
and it is so easy for us
to keep these academic
conversations in academic circles,
so very much interested in opening up
those communities of practice
and also interested
in Illit pedagogy.
He led it as a part of a learning process,
reaching out to students,
including student produced work
and thinking about works that are
useful in an anthology for teaching works
that are good to introduce students
to electronic literature.
We really were interested in
looking at a very wide
and very inclusive range
of born digital, hybrid
and digitally produced printworks,
and many of us have still a real soft spot
for the print book,
and very much interested in the ways
that digital and print can work together.
So we have been kind of really focusing
as much as we can
on on considering both,
especially hybrid works and,
and also really thinking
about how lacked everything.
Think about everything, read
everything brings up these one
practical, archival,
and also ethical considerations
around accessibility
and around our digital footprint.
So a quick answer to the
question that we've been dancing around,
what do we mean by Illit in 2026?
I feel like I have less of a grasp of this
than when I started,
which is maybe good thing.
Maybe the problem at typing
we've all been doing all the time,
and the thing we keep coming back to you
is that L.A.
in 2026 is anywhere that is fundamentally
shaped by its digital nature.
Which is huge
and massive
and I think wonderful in that massiveness.
It's also work that is necessarily
critically aware of and hopefully
critically discussing the platforms
and the systems that are in use.
And we're also really interested here
in access, prioritizing accessibility here
and accessibility
as a fundamental element of ROI.
The work and ROI archiving of that work,
and not just an afterthought.
And I think we're all doing that work.
But I do want to quickly shout out
Dan on our team for really always
being the champion
of accessibility in our progress.
Okay, so I'm going to
speak very, very briefly about the call
that we put out.
Our previous discussions have really
focused on this call and that's enough.
Looking back.
We want to look forward.
So I will just say this.
Our CFP was open from October
15th of 2025 to January 31st.
I think we extended for a month,
which is, you know, the regular
what you have to do,
and we received lots of great submissions
and Dan will talk about them briefly.
And the call was supported by a massive,
wonderful international team
of translators and consultants
who translated our call
into more than 15 languages
and did really great, you know,
boots on the ground work of disseminating
it across communities and to places that
we may have not known
about or been able to reach on our own.
So that was crucial for us,
and I hope that we I've included
some links here.
I hope that we're able to share
this slide deck
in some way, shape or form.
Beyond this, I don't know how
well I'm sure figure it out,
but here is a link to our call
and also our blog, where Dan
diligently updates about all things
about our submission process.
So after. Oh thank you. Zach.
And after singing their praises
800,000 times,
I think I now hand off to Dan.
Yep, I'm up next so I will
push us to the next one.
Okay, so based on Danny's great summary
of how we thought about the vision,
how we kind of incorporated that,
lots of really long discussions,
very fruitful discussions
about the kind of edge cases of Lid,
what is what could be what might have been
just kind of fascinating,
all the kind of temporal envelopes
you want to think about within
the English language of has been had,
could be ongoing,
you know, present
infinitives, subjunctive, whatever.
But what we are interested in
this section is kind of what we got.
So I'm going to go ahead
and move this forward.
About 400 submissions.
This is a little hard to figure out.
And I'm going to kind of explain why here.
So we got a large number
of individual submissions.
And I'm going to talk about some of
the statistics here in future slides.
But in some of them
they were entire subcultures.
And in a few cases they were entire sub
collections of hundreds of other works.
And so we had to kind of
draw a line somewhere and be like, well,
we can't accept a thousand works.
It's just too much work for for us.
But we can, you know,
ask folks to submit certain selections
from sub collections or certain selections
from other places that we think
are very important to include.
And that's been a lot of fruitful
conversations about that.
Know what is representative
of this community of practice.
As Danny was talking about
what is particularly representative
of these other forms of things,
lots of conversations about that.
So 400 ish, again, kind of loosely
in that window, because again,
some subcultures were were their own vast
and in some cases
potentially unknown
even to us kind of own communities
that have been ongoing
for quite a number of years.
So 400 issues.
What we've been saying,
and as Teddy was saying, I tend to be
the primary authorized the blog post,
if you're like, oh,
the blog post keeps saying 400 ish.
Well, yeah,
I keep I keep kind of writing that.
All right.
So a little bit of breakdown here.
So if you've been following the blog post
and again I recommend you do.
We've been roughly trying to do them
every 3 to 4 months.
So there will be one upcoming.
There might be another one
by the end of the year.
We'll kind of see how that goes.
And then we'll kind of
as we roll into the final long
stretch of production towards this,
there will be a kind of update on that
and then a final update.
So, you know, a handful of per year
kind of giving statistics.
So as I just mentioned,
90% of all submissions
had not been previously published.
This is a very exciting statistic
because collections like this
tend to get a lot of like, well,
I won this award.
And could you also put it
in this collection?
What's a worthy of inclusion? Of course.
But it's always very exciting because
we did not necessarily ask for those.
And suddenly a large number of people
who had new works, again,
that had not been other places.
And this includes, again,
soliciting and talking to
those communities of practice about what
are good representation works from you.
So very, very exciting thing.
Kind of in crunching those statistics,
we are also representative
of a very large international scope.
And Zach was talking about wonderful
consultants.
You know, 20
plus I think we're like 25 or something
by by current
calculations are that we may extend that.
We've been talking about potentially
bringing some more people on
to help us with certain things,
but we're looking at authors
from at least 18 countries.
It's a little bit difficult
to kind of break this down.
Some of our.
Metadata is a little bit interesting.
We're hoping to revise that as we kind of
get towards the end of the line.
We'll ask people to kind of
make sure they get clarify,
you know, if they might have put something
in the wrong field.
So we're looking at so this is off
I will say by like 6% ish.
So we'll kind of keep that in mind.
We will have better data
when we get towards the end.
Better metadata collection of this.
Again, individual authors never been
published for always very exciting to see.
We're also, as is probably common
to kind of sum up the get towards
the end of this particular slide.
Also seeing a large reliance on hypertext.
So HTML, CSS,
JavaScript are in major themes,
which we expect to see, but
we're also seeing a large number of works
and a large number of other platforms
and tools services.
Game engines are coming up quite a bit.
We're also having conversations
about what that means for preservation.
All of us are aware of the death of flash,
but we're also aware of the changing
kind of within web specifications as well.
Things like web, audio
and other things tend to change over time.
And so we want to be as kind of future
focused as we can.
So we are always keeping that in mind.
As Danny,
we're just saying we're constantly
having conversations
around accessibility and access.
What that means, what does it look like?
How do we kind of say things
for the future? What that means?
I was alluding to those of you
who made up caught the exhibition talk,
also talking about traversal videos.
That's been an ongoing conversation
as well as how do we preserve things?
Are we preserving traversals
and other things?
That's, I guarantee you, for next year's,
we'll be talking quite a bit about what
that kind of ended up as.
All right.
All right,
so let's talk a little bit
about the review process.
Sorry.
Navigating multiple digital things today.
It's always kind of fascinating.
All right.
So a little bit on the review.
So we have done
if you've been following the blog post
kind of multiple things
we have called rounds of reviewing.
The first was is what is this Ellen.
Which is kind of a funny question
we kept raising with at ourselves.
So imagine that again, 400
plus submissions.
Zach did some absolutely fantastic work
to kind of put us on a central database
that we have been really useful
to kind of sword and categorize
and use tags and kind of describe things
and various other ways.
That's been incredibly useful
to kind of add notes to things to be like,
oh, well, let's,
let's revisit this, or let's
go talk all through to find
if there's a different form.
Oh, we had difficulty accessing this, you
know, is there another form of whatever.
So we kind of did an initial round
within the kind of internal group
to kind of look at things.
This actually very little reduced it
because in some cases we couldn't access.
Someone said, oh,
you know, you had trouble with this.
Here's
a different link or here's a whatever.
So this kind of like subtract this
a little bit.
That also is where we got into this larger
sub collections of us looking like like,
hey, this is a huge community of like 100
plus works.
Do you want to select 5 or 6 or something?
Again, representative of that community.
So that kind of again
broader numbers down a little bit.
We also did a round one consultant review.
So the last blog post
talked about this process where again
we've got I think 25 ish people
that we
send it out to and we said, hey,
would you mind looking at this?
In a lot of cases,
that meant kind of assigning
people works within languages
they understood,
which was a considerable process
internally as us kind of figure out
how we can get the particular consultants
we need to review languages.
Some of us perhaps don't speak or cannot
read to kind of process that to give us.
There's initial input that ran
that went out and ran several weeks.
We got those a few weeks ago,
and then we kind of internally
went through those notes
and kind of made our own notes
or asked for a couple of cases, additional
information or a different context.
So that was around zero was like,
is it Ellet?
Round one was, hey,
could you help us just better understand
this work in some cases?
Again, kind of looking at forms and tropes
and certain cases
needing to get technical skills
for a particular subset
of those to be like,
what does this mean for you?
Can you give us better today
on these particular forms and tropes?
And was so really fantastic feedback
I can we cannot stress that enough.
From the consultants. Excellent work.
I will say the current info site
has has most of those folks.
Then we added to it
and we are in the process
of kind of making sure
we contribute all of that fantastic labor
as we kind of move forward
and potentially recruit more folks.
So I anticipate,
based on internal observations,
that that list of consultants
may grow longer as we move here.
All right.
So round two plus
we were
talking about this line
as we were preparing these
this presentation
that would we get finished in time
because we were kind of racing the clock
as we were kind of moving
through everything and, and slowly
making decisions and making notes
and again
contacting people and everything.
But we were finally very,
very it's not too long ago kind of finish
that we were able to scratch out
is currently finalizing.
We did finish.
So we finalized a series of review rounds.
So we were kind of internal.
Round two as we look at works more closely
so I will.
Yeah.
Yes. Thank you for clarifying it.
It was very not that far away.
We were very, very, very soon.
I was a little worried as I was traveling.
We may not be done with everything,
but we finally got through everything
as we got through this. All right.
So as
we were looking at, especially round two,
as Danny
was kind of saying from our initial vision
into looking at our initial submissions,
how we crafted the call for submissions,
what that looked like and our translation
work and all of that.
One of the things we also kind of
internally talked about is
what is our internal criteria, what is
important to us as a group that we think
could be deciding factor on, again,
thinking about particularly edge
cases of like, well, you know,
is this closer to something
that else that may exist
is something else a little more
representative of the types of forums,
lots of internal conversations and rounds,
lots and lots of conversations.
So I'm going to quickly
have it for things.
And then we will kind of move
into the next segment here.
So the four things real quick
review criteria, especially for the round
two plus of us
continuing to look at diversity
that continues to be a central pillar
of everything we discuss internally.
Diversity of language representation
is a strong point for all of us,
is making sure we are looking
beyond English into other languages
that may not have been represented in
other Elks or may have had representation,
other Elks, that we can continue to
strengthen and draw those connections in,
especially looking at countries,
communities of practice, continue
to be, again, a central pillar
of everything we're looking at.
How are people doing things?
What does this look like?
How can we best get representative works?
How best can we preserve access to them?
They're preserving access to
them is an ongoing conversation as well.
Platform criticality continues to be
a central pillar again, of all of this
critical, thoughtful engagement
with the platform and systems and use.
What does it mean
to use a particular tool,
particular game engine,
in particular system, particular language,
particular access point,
a particular genre form?
All of these are kind of driving
our considerations.
Lots of works have been
absolutely fantastic, and I'm very excited
to see what the final thing
and kind of what that all turns out.
But it continues to be kind of
a driving point of of a lot of this genre.
We tend to see
I mean, this is a community.
I was joking with someone earlier
in the conference.
We tend to see kind of cool things
of like Ojinaga emerges,
and then it becomes less dominant
and then becomes dominant
and becomes less dominant.
We kind of see this
as especially many of us mentor
undergraduate and graduate and sometimes
PhD researchers and fellows and things
where they kind of find a new form like,
oh, this is very exciting.
And then a potentially
a platform or tool goes down and it fades
or it may resurface in different ways.
So we continue to kind of look at John was
and forms and kind of things like that.
And making sure, you know, again
we're looking at Representative Works.
What is Ellet right now?
A kind of central theme around an idea
of a snapshot that will continue to appear
throughout this presentation.
Finally,
looking at major figures in the field,
there are a number of folks
who are very prolific.
There are a number of folks who aren't
as prolific for various reasons.
Some people are for their own reasons,
finding a balance between prioritizing new
and emerging voices
and existing voices continues
to be an ongoing conversation with us.
So as we get kind of closer to this,
folks will kind of see us continuing
to have this conversation to push and pull
of what might be representative of someone
who has shown up at multiple times,
and other Elks versus new folks
versus emerging folks.
And we kind of see these cycles.
So ongoing conversation with all of us.
There are no kind of final decisions.
Yet as we get to the end,
there are some final decisions
within round two,
but that
continues to be a conversation of us
wanting to support new and exciting work,
and also very interesting work from people
who are known in the field to do
excellent stuff. All right.
Finally.
Oh yes, I get to talk about Jen.
I was like, what else is coming
up? Yes. So
as folks, all who are part
of this conference in real time,
the online exhibition also had
a generative AI disclosure section.
That is also something
we are continuing to discuss.
As Danny was mentioning,
we had lots of internal conversations
about what that might look like,
how we would ask for it, transparency
around different things.
People have been generally very fantastic
about telling us, hey, we use this model,
this version, did this work.
Process stuff has been again
a central focus of ours.
We did ask for transparency.
If you if folks saw
if you might be you in the audience.
I don't know if folks used it
what it looked like.
We asked again for ethical considerations
around a lot of this,
critical considerations around copyright
data ethics, and a lot of those things.
We are still having those ongoing
conversations.
Licensing continues
to be an issue with a number of works
that we're having,
that environmental impact of AI stuff.
As Danny was saying,
there's lots of works
made with AI within this current snapshot.
There are works made without AI.
There are many people who have
strong feelings on both sides of that.
We were trying to take those
in consideration of how people feel about
that.
We have, as Denny was also saying,
gotten some quite negative
feedback for even including AI at all,
which was
deeply concerning to me
because I was a person who was
who got a lot of that kind of
I tanked a lot of it.
He was a game term.
We also got some private emails and, well,
I will not say who emailed us.
They said that based on the feedback
they had seen to just the call,
they would not submit anything,
which was, you know, quite troubling.
So we are continuing
to have that conversation
about what this means, what it looks like.
But I will say we have heard
from a large number of folks
behind the scenes of kind of folks that
like, well, I was thinking about this, but
I saw what happened,
or I would have liked to done this,
but I saw whatever,
or I'm thinking about this.
Yes, we are again,
having those conversations,
the online kind of online exhibition stuff
that happens on a regular basis
might also be a place
for some of those works
that we have also told folks that like,
hey, if you didn't catch us
this time, there's lots of other things
that kind of contribute to that.
On that somewhat down note,
I will turn it over,
I believe, to the next person.
Thank you all.
So timeline.
It's already July 2026,
so we're basically at the half
point of our work.
There it is.
So we've we've gone over the vision,
the goal for submissions, the review.
And we're
now working on the final selection or
we'll be working on the final selection,
the development and the publication,
hopefully within a year or for next year.
So for all the submitters
who maybe in the audience right now,
if you submitted your work,
you'll be hearing from us by early fall.
We're hoping to have a week
or two vacation after the conference,
and then take it up
to to to do our final selection
and communicate with you all.
So please bear with us. Be patient.
We're going as fast as we can.
However, from all the all the stuff
that we've been receiving,
we've been seeing
some very interesting trends
that really translate this,
this kind of truism that we that we talk
about the collections every time
that they reflect the current state of,
of of it at the time, or
they provide a snapshot of, of the field
and so on. No.
And one of the questions
that we asked ourselves in one of our
very long meetings
is whether this is the saddest ELC yet.
And I'll tell you why
this is the case.
What are the trends that we're finding?
On the one hand, we're finding
what we're calling the sucky internet,
basically, allusions
and very interesting critical uses
of the very tedious tasks
that the internet now requires of us,
like doom scrolling,
answering a million captured CAPTCHAs,
answering a million.
Are you about kind of tricks and games
and puzzles and whatnot that have been
very interestingly deployed to create,
you know, very beautiful, very engaging
works?
Similarly,
we're finding a lot of vintage interfaces
from windows XP and many others.
Really an interesting look at perhaps
we are hypothesizing
whether this is, you know,
a look at the at a moment
when the internet was not as sucky.
This information
really kind of like runs the gamut
from Covid, which I guess
we're still catching some of the works
that were produced around the time
of the previous collection in 2021.
And of course, the relationships
of technology and fascism
and disinformation,
how it is used to promote
that kind of discourse
is very, very prevalent.
A fourth
trend that we've identified so far
is some kind of historical recovery.
We're finding a lot of archival images
being put to use
to recover, archives to recover,
to to repair, perhaps
certain historical injustices.
Again, a very interesting
look at the past that seems
fairly novel in the submissions
that we've received.
Climate change is also
very present in a lot of the
in a very big percentage
of the of the submissions.
Yeah, I like that.
You'll see.
And certification edition
with a lot of allusion
to water creatures, plants
in various poetics for poetic forms.
So that's also something
that we're looking at a lot.
And again, the prevalence of AI.
So there's a lot of
AI is doing awful things.
It's embroiled
and tangled in a lot of concerning stuff.
And also at the same time,
a lot of interesting explorations of it.
The way
that we're trying to understand
this thing is
whether it's a different post
digital moment of Iliad or
I'm thinking
we're thinking about the possibility of
and how when it was first proposed,
I want to say about 15 years ago,
there was a big focus on esthetics
and and the meaning of media,
I guess, with less consideration
for the politics of technology
and the material conditions
that propel them.
And we think this is different.
We're seeing, like the posterior
more as an attention to the politics
and the material conditions of tech,
which in turn yield
a specific media engagement
with the static.
So it's kind of like a turning around
of this, of these ideas that have been
around the field for a long time,
but really just
responding to the current moments.
And we're further hypothesizing.
And this, you know,
this may change in a year, I don't know.
But for the hypothesizing that
this could mean an enhanced polarization
of elite, we've, we've we've heard
perhaps within the field
and outside the field
that it has
not always been very political.
But I think this is a
this is definitely a change
that we're seeing, like from the
from the criticality of the platforms,
from the topics that get addressed,
from the concerns that we see.
I think we're seeing a very concerted
engagement to, to the political media
landscape that there is like that
underlying political landscape, for sure.
In summary,
you don't have to care about all of this.
This is a little bit of of an inner joke
that we wanted to share with you
of, you know, trying to
simplify the experience of going through
this year, of receiving
and reading a lot of fascinating words
that, you know,
you may or may not necessarily care
that much about.
And I think it's over to you.
Yeah. So I kind of wrapping it up here.
We just want to give a big
thanks and shout out to several groups
and people that have been supporting
this UCF for seeing us or supporting us
at our editorial retreat a few weeks
ago, and Seltzer and John Murray
for hosting us and taking us to cool
Orlando restaurants and
all of our translators and consultants.
Many of you are here in right now,
and it's so great to see you all.
And we're we're extremely grateful
for your work.
It was it has helped our conversations
tremendously to have a starting point
and a frame of reference for for the work
that you've been able to review.
So thank you very much for that.
Also, lots of the past ALC
editors, editors of past collections
have been generous with their time
and advice and and yeah and PD
thanks for
your has been very helpful in design
and helping us
think about what ELC five will look like.
So thanks. Thanks to you all. Yeah.
Another shout out to PT.
And speaking of which,
so I wanted to mention this.
We have some stickers.
I well I can't reach the boxes over there,
but these are some stickers.
I'd love to send you some of these
in the mail if you would like them.
So PD came up with a design concept
there, and I
have a bunch of them printed out there
and I side quality stickers.
They'll go on a water bottle pretty well.
I don't have one on my water bottle,
but yeah, there you go.
Thanks.
So if they.
Awesome. Yeah.
I can't show that it's on my laptop,
which I can't.
I mean, I'm looking at my laptop
right now, so I can't turn it around.
But if you'd like some, there's a web
form.
Just send that.
Submit that, and I will get those
into the mail to you as soon as I can.
And I believe this is our last slide.
So thanks everyone.
Thanks for your attention.
And I think we have some time for Q&A.
I've comment and question.
Thank you so much for all this work.
And so I'm holding on to all the archives
for all the Elks.
Right.
And I want to encourage you
to do more of the printing.
And we've talked about this.
Zach, thank you for the stickers.
And anytime you make something,
put the year on it,
because it's still going backwards
and looking at wonderful ephemera
from like, I don't know, gig 2.0 and go,
what year was that?
And have to go look it up.
So date everything you possibly can
and make lots of paper stuff,
even if you never print it.
Send me the copies,
the digital copy.
We will definitely.
Yeah, we will definitely do that.
Thank you.
Any questions
from folks
we can attempt to answer things?
I will say I was just told
there is a bug with the site,
so I will get on that this afternoon.
We'll see about fixing something.
Yeah okay
I'm mid central Florida thunderstorm.
So if you hear any thunder in the pack
it's just what's going on.
I was wondering if you could talk
a little bit more about the communities
of practice that you were discovering,
kind of outside the literature
like community and
and like where they are,
who they are,
or maybe like where we can look for them.
Yeah, that's a great question.
I mean, as you know,
I've talked about, like, sometimes
I have this
hunch that there are people doing
cool work and sharing it online
that don't know the word,
the phrase electronic literature.
And so that was that really motivated
our, our decision
to recruit consultants
to try to connect with those communities.
And also, like the four of us
are connected to different communities.
So we've been trying to to reach those.
I think the different elit friendly
periodicals are useful
as a nexus of that kind of thing.
So the ones that you mentioned yesterday
also thinking of.
Events like like word hack,
I mean, those are places where different
people would come together and tune in.
Maybe that wouldn't
necessarily be at this conference.
And so that was another form of outreach.
And also honestly, just kind of like
looking on places like itch.io
and clicking through different tags until,
you know, seeing what's out there.
So we are
since I mentioned that
we have the submissions,
we're looking at things,
but we are still trying to figure out
kind of where the gaps are
and where we feel like there are
potential opportunities to include
more of those kinds of works
from specific communities or languages.
So there will there may continue to be
some outreach in that, that direction.
So yeah, if you if you know
of specific adjacent communities
that we should be aware of,
then please tell us.
I think also fruitful has been looking at
global kind of small press communities.
I'm particularly involved in the small
press community appearing in Canada.
In Ontario.
Nobody say anything to me about fires,
by the way.
I can't talk about it right now.
Just don't talk to me about it.
But we have a really rich small press
community up here,
and that's been kind of a great
place to mine and find people
who are doing really cool
digital digital work.
Also kind of,
I guess I don't know if this is
maybe our blind spot area where
we don't know too much about or whatever,
but we had been pretty outside
of the blockchain NFT conversation.
I think that sometimes
our community tends to be
a bit more sighted
and a more creative sided.
And the other half, the other half of me
that is not academic
is that dev is a web developer.
So that side of me gets really embroiled
in that kind of blockchain
NFT world,
which has been helpful and really shown us
where our edges are
and how those are getting
brushed, brushed up against.
Been a very cool process.
And Andrew, I used to live
very close to Pinnacle Lane,
and for a long time there was a
you're supposed to go
with a glass of water and fill up.
One part of it says a lake.
So if you go with some water and
fill up the lake, that's really important.
I did see a comment about somebody
asking us to go back to,
and I will say this for people
who are looking at control.
Slide 15 of what we mean by islet in 2026.
I'm happy to do that,
but I think we'd have to move.
That might be a Zach thing
to move us back to that thing.
But you know, you all can move slides.
Yeah.
Anybody?
Well, the four of us, not everybody.
Sorry,
I just noticed my computer is freaking up.
All right, well, as one of us
is freaking out on my computer.
Yeah,
I will sit in the chat. I'd be curious.
To see your comments on.
And I asked that very much in the spirit
of being like, in a discipline
that's often accused of just incorporating
everything like we are.
Just.
So I totally get around that.
There's so much thing,
there's so many things that we would
consider to be close to our practice,
and we want to bring them home
and claim them.
But I'm just wondering if you discuss
kind of the tension,
I think around that to around people
who might not want to imagine
that their practice is reducible to us.
Yeah, that's a good question.
Or do you want to
you have a Muted so yeah for sure
I mean I remember having this conversation
I was really interesting to think about
stuff that hasn't
made it into the collections
or that much into the field,
except this year I've seen it a lot
like fanfiction and just fan communities.
And and we were thinking
about like the process
and this idea of how
works that are fundamentally
shaped by the digital nature
and how those communities
and the production that they make
may not have, like some of
the classical contours of Elliot with,
I don't know, interaction or animation
or game dynamics or generation and so on.
But they really do depend on digital
technologies to exist and to take shape.
So we definitely wanted to include
something like that
because we consider the digital aspects
to be really conditions of possibility
for their existence.
And that is the case with many others.
Like Denny
mentioned, a lot of the hybrid works.
That's the same thing.
Like definitely like we've
we've we're still thinking
about the matter of print matter,
but there's print matter
that is absolutely determined
by their digital conditions
and their digital nature.
So that that was expands
and ends up, yeah, including a lot more
than has been included there.
But I think the yeah, that
that fundamental idea of how it's shapes
and how it's how the digital becomes
a condition of possibility
is critical to, to to our understanding.
Thank you.
And also said
we were interested
in the initial recruitment of consultants,
kind of because like let's say there
a pocket of people doing cool work
that we think is lit or could be lit.
We didn't want to just send a mass
email to everyone and be like,
you should submit stuff.
We wanted to see if do we know somebody
or a friend of a friend or something?
And is there a way that we could find
someone
who is already connected to that community
that could be a liaison and help us,
you know, help send people
our way as opposed to us
kind of reaching in from
the outside and trying to
vacuum in everything.
Yeah.
So I was going to build on that as well.
So as someone who it feels like
it's my primary life,
teaches game design and game development
without going to deep into the rabbit
hole of the kind of adventures
that have been going on
in the last several decades.
Within those communities of practice,
many people have moved away.
Especially independent developers
have moved away from the term game.
So in a move to other things which might
be or could be a number of other things.
So it's also kind of interesting,
as many of us are aware,
kind of within academia, of claiming
certain categorizations that may help us
get more eyes or a greater audience
or a greater focus on our work.
So that is also also a kind of interesting
push pull within this as well, is,
you know, it might be worthwhile
for a number of folks
to claim elit and away from game,
just as a kind of sub example.
But there might be other works as well
that might be more expansive
within other things.
I'm going
to start to build on the question.
Oh gosh, I just saw it.
Sorry. Disappeared there.
And then I'm going to I'm going
to turn this over to somebody else.
So Leo, ask what is literature?
So Leo, you may be surprised to find out
or not surprised at all.
As a former editor of ELC, stuff
that we spent
quite a bit of time
discussing this about what is literature?
What is electronic literature, and
is there meaning in a kind of hyphenate
or hybrid of electronic literature
that does not exist within?
There's other things.
We did have an intense conversation.
The other scholars with me here
are far more versed in this than I am,
so if they would like to contribute,
I would have to be quiet
and just not along to their brilliance.
But I will.
I will hand it off to whatever
you all want to say on that topic.
I think we settled
because
we were going with the idea of like,
there has to be some kind of language
or some kind of words,
but I think we went a little bit further
to that and settle on Danny.
Correct me if I'm wrong, was it a vocation
of language or invocation of language?
Something like that.
I like both, yeah, both feel great.
Yeah,
yeah, I think I think you suggested
the term or poetics is kind of a filter.
Like if there's a poetics like something
some kind of emergent meaning,
some kind of to it, something
that, you know, reaches out,
those are the kinds of things that could
have a narrative feature, could have a
could be poetic poetry or imagery.
I mean, there are lots of different ways
that that might happen,
but there is something,
something that's,
you know, connecting to us in some way.
Yeah.
I do think that we hit a point
in all of these discussions where
we really kind of stopped caring
and that it really became.
Yeah, like,
what have you mean by Eliot in 2026?
Sure. Like,
because that distinction started feeling
maybe not very youthful and,
and I'm, I think, yeah, we all came
with our own kind of wheel houses
and we really broke those down.
I think that that's why it's been such
an enriching process is because
as we start up this definition,
it became really kind of almost
not interesting to have the discussion
about the definition at all,
which is, I don't know, maybe where
you all have been this whole time, but
I think I was as stuck in my literary hole
for a little bit.
And now,
the submissions that
we've received pushed our boundaries
in such fantastic ways.
Yeah, by vibe at it. And now. Sure.
Yeah, sure.
I think that's a good term.
Yeah, yeah. If we could accept.
I know if we could accept it all,
we probably would have.
If we could have an anthology
of every single thing
that.
I think there's a place in our heart
for that.
So it became kind of what story
do we want to tell
about this work and about this community
and all these intersections?
Yeah, that's a great way to put it.
Yeah, I agree
Mark.
Let's see if your hand up.
Yeah.
First of all, thank you so much.
The four of you
for all the work you putting into this.
I mean, it really
is a gift to the community.
I'm also so sorry to hear that
you've taken some heat
for even considering AI
and the notion of AI.
If it helps, I think previous ELC editors
have also received
heat for whatever kind of things
they were tackling at the time.
So it's it's it's nothing new,
although AI is definitely more divisive.
But I was just thinking back
to last year's
conference theme, if I remember,
I know Caitlin couldn't correct me.
Wasn't it
love letters to the past and future?
And if we can think
about the ELC collection as like
a love letter to the future.
What do you hope
maybe 5 or 6 years from now,
when the next ELC team
might be working on their collection?
What what do you hope that has been
the legacy of your work here?
Well,
one, this is something we talked about
a decent amount in Orlando.
You know, we are closed
kind of right, as things
like Cloud Code were becoming
much more widely available and adopted.
And and so I think we have a hunch
that the next
the next you'll see you'll see
volume 6th May deal with a much larger
submission pool.
That's one possibility.
If it's suddenly easier for essentially
everybody to very quickly create dozens of
literary works in an electronic modality
like that, that could create a
slot problem.
I guess that in that sense, this might be
a really important opportunity
at this moment as as
we might be transitioning into
that kind of place with digital writing
to kind of say what's interesting,
as we're kind of on that,
on that edge,
as we're kind of moving into that.
So I think we have a really important,
you know, one of my slides earlier
was talking about like, what's at stake.
And I think that's
one of the things at stake is like,
this may be our last chance
to talk really clearly about what
is different about digital writing with
and without AI tools.
And I think including both in the scope
of what
we're considering is how we
we think we're having.
We're trying to create a space
for that conversation
and for that kind of criticality
to be visible.
Yeah, I think there's
I think it's interesting.
I mean, I think that is one possibility
is like, yeah, just a flood of AI stuff.
The other possibility is that AI just
kind of becomes part of the background.
You know, it would not be,
I think somebody mentioned in a panel
the other day, but like technology
kind of goes through these phases, right.
So like 40 years ago
would have been pretty interesting to try
to work with email as a platform
for making literary work.
But it's just part of it's
just a background process now.
It's just part of how we all communicate.
So it's not as exciting just to kind of
go straight for like to use that
as the thing like that, as the novelty
of a particular literary work necessarily.
And maybe AI goes that way. Maybe.
Or maybe AI is such a fundamental
sea change shift
in how we think about writing that it's
there are different kinds of consequences
that will be interesting to see.
I'm definitely interested
in capturing all these sort of.
Like chaotic and emergence and messy
kind of steps into digital writing with AI
or thinking about creativity theory,
because the the early sloppy, weird stuff
from,
let's say like four years
ago, it's kind of hard to reproduce.
It's kind of hard to capture.
So if our collection can do some work
to preserve
that moment,
I think that would be really valuable.
If I may add something.
Also, building on on the on the trends
that we've seen, Mark, I think.
I mean,
the matter of being enthusiastic
about technology
and creating with different technologies
is definitely still there.
And the field probably depends on that.
But similarly or conversely
or simultaneously, I don't know what
what connector to use here.
There's I feel like
I'm seeing a lot more permission
to be angry at technology
and at the material conditions
of technology
than in previous collection
and in previous technological moments.
So I think that's going to be interesting
for the field to that.
Yeah, there is the enthusiasm,
but but the fold is much
more evident in the, in the creative works
that we're seeing right now.
So perhaps that will,
that will change or scholarship
perhaps that will change or practice to.
Just to kind of add on this,
I was given a pause to see
if Danny wanted to talk,
and perhaps, perhaps
you would go around and have thoughts
after I talk for a second.
I think I have a kind of
an interesting approach to legacy
as it applies to this particular thing.
Some of you perhaps know I've been part
of kind of various open source communities
that have tempted to standardize
or great specifications for things,
and it's always
a very fascinating experience to attempt
to capture something that it kind of
has been going on
and put it into a framework
that other people
can kind of understand in the future,
because inevitably you miss something
or you didn't quite capture it,
or there was a compromise
that came a part of a standardization.
I realized I'm getting a little bit
in the computer science land here,
but part of that kind of journey,
though, is incredibly important.
And I think part of what
we have tried to continually
show is our
transparency along this process of like,
here's what our thinking was
and here's why we were doing this
and here's why we were doing that,
and here's our vision and here's
our thoughts, here's our criteria.
So my greatest hope,
and I think many of us
who kind of also exist
within the kind of educator space
is that we are providing a ladder
towards the future, right?
We are hoping helping people build towards
whatever it comes next
for as much as possible.
I know I had the online exhibition
the other day.
I had a little spill on hope,
but like that is a central part
of my kind of pedagogy and practice.
Among
a lot of things is like trying to build.
Sometimes you can't build a better future,
but sometimes you can try
not to make it worse.
That is a kind of life philosophy
I follow in a lot of places is like,
we just try not to make it worse, right?
If we can make it better,
we can make it better,
but we just try not to make it worse.
And so as much as possible,
having this kind of open standards, open
talks, open thoughts and criteria
and visions, you know, we have reiterated
multiple times, like the fantastic work
of previous Elk's talking to those folks,
learning from their feedback
and being like, oh,
we would have done this and
we wanted to do this, and we caught this.
Well, we couldn't catch this or,
you know, oh,
we were thinking about this metadata thing
and oh, would be great to do whatever.
All of that is fantastic.
And so hopefully we can kind of continue
to be part of this ongoing chain
to ten, 15 years down the future.
You know, who knows what
technologies may break in the meantime,
but hopefully we're continuing to kind of
building towards a less worse
future, a less sucky internet.
I don't know.
I don't know what that looks like.
And maybe I'll just
close by saying, like,
if I could pick the legacy
for this LC five,
I want us to be the punk ones.
It feels like it's been
I feel like we've been the punk
this whole time.
I don't know, it feels good.
It feels like all of those things
kind of coming together.
That responsibility to community,
that underlying politicization,
the kind of joy in the anger.
It feels very punk to me.
I feel hardcore with this group.
Is there a more punk
emoji than the email one
we might need to investigate in something
with more safety pins?
Someone get me off camera.
Lot of great conversations
in the chat, by the way.
I mean, we've all been kind of chiming in
and responding there,
but if there's something
that anyone wants to bring to the surface
to talk about, please do.
I'm just going back through.
I guess we just have a few more
minutes in this session. So
yes. And I also want to tag into
Zack just said if anybody kind of in
real time has any things
they would like to see in future
blog posts,
we are kind of open discussing that.
I know we've been kind of
for fronting our statistics
about what that looks like in our process,
but if people are interested in like,
what platforms are you seeing
and what forms and whatever,
like, you know, we can
we can run some statistics.
We're very healthy.
You know, it's
kind of interesting thing of like,
how do we want to present that?
But if people are interested
in like particular things, let us know
and we will we will attempt to meet you.
A good question.
We we did get a decent amount
of submissions,
not on behalf of the author,
because we haven't hit that
like final acceptance point yet.
We actually haven't reached out
to too many of those individual authors,
so we haven't actually had a conversation
with authors themselves about
whether or not
they consider their work.
But certainly we have had submissions
on behalf of works
that aren't considered
or wouldn't are not for
formats or communities that violate.
I would urge you,
when you do have those conversations,
to archive them on paper.
For Dini,
that would be a really interesting
look at what he lit is from the outside.
Yeah, that's a good idea.
I'm going to respond
to a comment real quick.
So so Teagan mentioned we'd love to know
what forums we're seeing.
And so obviously that would be part of the
and the second part of this,
could you provide a public metadata set.
So I do not have enough time
to go in the details of that,
but there were extensive conversations
around the fantastic work.
The next is done on their Elms format.
People may have noticed that was used
as part of the online exhibition
for this year.
I also had lots of conversations
with the cell, who does fantastic work
on their end about kind of how we think
about metadata, what that looks like.
Those are ongoing,
but we I would really like to kind of
push forward again, having that
public data so people can easily
pass it on into these other
sometimes longer lived archives as well.
So yes, we are
there's absolutely part of this as well.
I will tag on.
I don't think I mentioned it as part
of the online exhibition, but there is.
I'll have to double check.
I'm almost certain
there is like a giant metadata
thing of like, here's
the metadata of everything.
It's just one file and it matches.
Well, it's very close to the Elm
schema, minus the new AI think.
But I do want to give like a
like a one minute of time
in case somebody's got important question.
Yeah. And
we can provide or we are
we do have that metadata like in a
anonymized sense for the submissions.
So like we will definitely have,
you know, when it's collected
published will be putting that out.
But we also are trying to capture
that and organize
that as we're
just kind of looking through submissions,
including things
that probably won't make it in.
We're still going to keep track of what
what bucket
does this go in that kind of thing.
And we'll share that as, as we can.
Fantastic.
Well, on that note,
I want to thank our collective
not just for these talks,
but for just the incredible amount of work
that just described and the incredible
amount of work still to come
to bring this collection fully to life.
Thank you all.
This is incredible, and we really appreciate this volunteer labor on an epic scale.
Thank you.
Very exciting.
So looking forward.
And with that
we are moving into our next block
starting up at 215.
So please.